If Nancy doesn't wake up screaming, she won't wake up at all.
A Nightmare on Elm Street is a horror film directed by Wes Craven.
Teenagers in a small town are dropping like flies, apparently in
the grip of mass hysteria causing their suicides.
A cop's daughter, Nancy Thompson, traces the cause to child molester Fred
Krueger, who was burned alive by angry parents many years before.
Krueger has now come back in the dreams of his killers'
children, claiming their lives as his revenge.
Nancy and her boyfriend, Glen, must devise a plan to lure the monster
out of the realm of nightmares and into the real world...
Nancy Thompson, played by Heather Langenkamp.
Freddy Krueger, played by Robert Englund.
Lieutenant Thompson, played by John Saxon.
Marge Thompson, played by Ronee Blakley.
Glen Lantz, played by Johnny Depp.
Rod Lane, played by Jsu Garcia.
A Nightmare on Elm Street is a 1984 American supernatural slasher film
written and directed by Wes Craven and produced by Robert Shaye.
It is the first installment in the A Nightmare on Elm Street franchise and stars Heather Langenkamp, John
Saxon, Ronee Blakley, Robert Englund as Freddy Krueger, and Johnny Depp in his film debut.
The film's plot concerns a group of teenagers who are targeted by Krueger, an undead child killer who murders
teenagers through their dreams, as retribution against their parents who burned him alive.
Craven filmed A Nightmare on Elm Street in Los Angeles
on an estimated budget of $1.1 million.
It was one of the first films produced by New Line Cinema, who by that point mostly distributed films, leading the company
to become a successful mini-major film studio and earning it the nickname "The House that Freddy Built".
The film is credited with carrying on many tropes found in low-budget horror films of the 1970s and 1980s, originating in John Carpenter's Halloween (1978),
including the morality play that revolves around sexual promiscuity in teenagers resulting in their eventual death, leading to the term "slasher film".
Critics and film historians state that the film's premise is the struggle to define the distinction
between dreams and reality, manifested by the lives and dreams of the teens in the film.
Later critics praise the film's ability to transgress "the boundaries between
the imaginary and real", toying with audience perceptions.
A Nightmare on Elm Street was released on November 9,
1984, and grossed $57.1 million worldwide.
The film received critical acclaim upon its release, and has since been
considered to be one of the greatest horror films ever made.
In 2021, A Nightmare on Elm Street was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry
by the Library of Congress as being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film spawned a franchise consisting of six sequels, a television series, a crossover with
Friday the 13th, various other merchandise, and a remake of the same name.
The film was followed by A Nightmare on Elm Street 2: Freddy's Revenge (1985).
The film explores themes of dreams, nightmare, psychopath, sleep, child murder.
The tone is dark and intense.